<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons humbly offered, proving it is inconsistent with the interest of England, that the civil magistrate should put the penal-laws in execution against Protestant dissenters</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58260</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12801071</idno>
  <idno type="VID">94045</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240959698</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6586</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12801071</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58260)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94045)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 776:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons humbly offered, proving it is inconsistent with the interest of England, that the civil magistrate should put the penal-laws in execution against Protestant dissenters</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Janeway,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Protestants --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94045:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94045:1"/>
            <p>REASONS Humbly OFFERRED, Proving it is inconsistent with the <hi>Interest of England,</hi> THAT THE CIVIL MAGISTRATE Should put the PENAL-LAWS In Execution against <hi>Protestant Dissenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Janeway.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:94045:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94045:2"/>
            <head>Reasons humbly offered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THAT 'tis the greatest Interest of all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant States, and particularly of <hi>England,</hi> To give Liberty to men of differing Apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Protestant Religion, is evident; if we consider, That a Prince or State by imposing the Principles of any one Party in Religion, makes himself of that Party, and engages all the rest against him. 'Tis no way prudent for a <hi>Prince,</hi> when his Subjects consist of many differing Judgments, to resolve to have them all of one mind, (a thing impracticable) or else to be their declared Enemy and Persecutor; 'tis a ready way to interrupt his own quiet and repose, without any other effect; for he will never by force and violence unite men in one Opinion, those Differences will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be fomented, and all Animosities arising thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and men rather fixed and confirmed by such Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than any way removed from their Principles by it. 'Tis not the having several parties in Religion under a State, that is in it self dangerous, but 'tis the persecuting of them that makes them so. First, It puts them all under discontent, and then unites them together in such discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; <hi>Thuanus,</hi> a wise States-man, saith, <hi>Heretici, qui pace data factionibus franguntur, persecutione uniuntur contra rem publicam.</hi> Those who in their Principles largely differ
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94045:3"/>from each other, when they come to be all bound up together in one common volumn, and linked in the same chain of Persecution and Suffering, will be sure to twist themselves into an united Opposition, to such an undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguishing severity: Whereas the thing in it self rightly considered, So many divided Interests and Parties in Religion, are much less dangerous than any, and may be prudently managed to ballance each other, and to become generally more safe, and useful to a State, than any united party or interest whatever. He that, is suffered to enjoy under a State the freedom of his Religion, when differing from the publick Profession, has not only the common tye of a Subject upon him, for his protection as a man, but the cumulative obligation, and thanks to pay for his Indulgence as a Christian under such a Character. Subjects in such a posture, as they will ever be studious of an opportunity, to testifie their grateful fidelity, and by some eminent Service to lay up a stock of Merit, that may secure their future quiet; so they will of any, most careful not to forfeit so pleasing an Indulgence, by falling under a publick displeasure. A Prince in such a state of things, by making himself a common Father to the whole Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Religion, though made up of some differences within it self, will be secured not only of that common Homage of Obedience and Subjection, but with it, that more noble, of the Hearts and Affections of all his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Subjects. To say any party in Religion is disaffected to a State, and therefore not fit for such favour, when such disaffection, if it be, does plainly arise from the Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the State against them, in that case; the reason why favour should not be show'd, is remov'd by showing of it: for as persecuting men for their Religion, must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94045:3"/>disgust them; so giving them the freedom of it, must needs equally oblige them. 'Tis no true measure to take of any parties in Religion, to say the one are better Subjects than the other, when the one are savoured and countenanced, and the other still kept under and oppressed; There is no reason, but to belive, there is an equal Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in all, to love that Prince or State, where they find favour and protection; 'tis a common disposition runs in the blood of all men; And by how much the Principles of any party are less taking and plausible, the less dangerous still is that party; and as they will need favour more than others, so they must needs lye proportionably secured to a State, by the Obligations put upon them.</p>
            <p>Take it for Truth which is commonly affirmed, That all such for whom Liberty is at any time desir'd, are men full of Faction and full of Error: For the first, 'tis certain, Persecution will not only continue, but foment such Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and give it a plausible pretence to justifie it self up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereas a Liberty granted in matters of Conscience, will either wholly win such men to a due and hearty Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as finding themselves in a posture they cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to mend, or else will lay them open to such appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent justice for punishment, and bring them under such a general contempt, as shall leave them strip'd of all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensions, and render them wholly inconsiderable. 'Tis marvellous prudence to separate between <hi>Conscience</hi> and <hi>Faction,</hi> which can never be, but by a liberty for the one, that so they may distinctly punish the other: He that hath liberty granted to worship God according to his Conscience, and yet is not satisfied, but continues trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome, makes every body ready to be his Executioner, and makes that discovery which could never have been
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94045:4"/>made before; that Faction was his end, and Conscience but the pretended means; such men will not only lye open to the States just severity, but to the hatred of all men, who do generally dislike ill actions most, when they come from men of the best pretensions.</p>
            <p>Punish men for their Religion, because you judge them Factious, and mix all together, and you fall into this dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble error; either you punish men for Faction, that deserve it not, and so, besides a piece of injustice, do what you can to make those Enemies who are not, nor would not be so; or else those that are so, you give them the pretence of Conscience to justifie themselves in what ever suffering comes upon them: When people differing from the publick Religion, meet to worship God, and are seized and punished for so doing, the Magistrate saith, <hi>He pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth for Faction;</hi> they say, <hi>They suffer for Religion.</hi> And all people who see the actual punishment inflicted, for things relating to Conscience and Religion, will be sure to believe and pitty them, and be ready to condemn the State. A due Separation, as 'tis best to be made, so 'twill, only by a liberty given, be obtained; He that intends nothing but to give God the Homage of his Conscience, will have freedom to do it; and he that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that has other ends and aims, will be justly punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it: But for a State to imbibe a general belief, that all who differ from the State Religion, are facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Civil Power, and not to be suffered, and so to punish them as such, and if they be not so, to tempt them thereby to be so, is to do an act of injustice to them, and to forfeit their own prudence towards them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</p>
            <p>For the errors you may suppose men possessed withall,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94045:4"/>as an eager persecution is apt to make the professors of them, think them more than ordinary Truths, and themselves some great men in maintaining them; so it makes others seek after that, when driven into a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, which were it in the open streets, no man would Regard. He that preaches and writes under restraint, that restraint begets him readers and hearers, that would else pass through the World with very little notice taken of him; things difficult and hard to be come by, carry some weight in mens expectancy: Foolish and absurd Opinions are onely put to Nurse by persecution, and by that made to have something in the concerns and fears of others, which has indeed nothing in it self. The hiding men by a keen pursuit after them, in the profession of such things, keeps them alive; whereas if they were openly preached, written, and discoursed of, the folly of them would appear such, as not only others, but the men themselves would be ashamed and aweary of them: Besides, punishing men for Religion, where there are several parties, laies a Foundation of endless troubles, and perpetual feuds; for that ill Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and anger, which makes one party, when Prevailing, to suppress and punish the rest, propagates still the same anger and dislike in the parties punished, and begets by such provocation, a certain resolution to retort the same again, and a readiness to embrace all opportunities to effect it; whereas that party that once gives liberty to the rest, buries all those evils, and unites all in the common union of their own interest and security. It will be impossible to find out a way for men of differing Judgments in Religion, to live together, and enjoy the common advantages which as men they may afford one
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94045:5"/>to another; unless they exercise an Indulgence to each other, in that variety they stand in as Christians. Where there are many differences, and a State denies any liberty, but strictly imposeth the State Religion upon all, the case always falls out to be, that the earnest desire of that we call <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> lies glowing in the Embers of mens discontent, and is a thing in it self so popular, a thing of so great evidence of reason, when it may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scoursed upon equal terms, and so much the concern of every man, but the present Imposers, that 'tis very apt to kindle and flame out, and upon any strait or emergency of the State, either by Forreign War, or Domestick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision, to make such an Earthquake, as may endanger the whole; 'Tis most Prudent in a State to give Liberty, where there is least power to demand it, those may be gained by giving it, that may prove dangerous in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it; to force and pen men up in such things is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unnatural, and will, like Wind penn'd up in the Earth, or the Sea shut up by Banks, break out at one time or another with the greater violence. Liberty in Religion was never yet denied in a Protestant State, but it had first or last a mischievous effect; to instruct men in Protestant Principles, and then put a yoke of Uniformity upon them, has no more proportion in it, than to educate a man at <hi>Geneva,</hi> that is to live at <hi>Rome,</hi> and to breed him a <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist</hi> whom you intend for a <hi>Papist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were there no other reason to make a Prince or a State out of love with punishing men for Religion, and matters of that nature, this were sufficient, to consider such pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment ever falls upon the most honest of his Subjects in every differing party; men of loose jugling principles, and unfound Hearts, will be sure to escape the Net; only the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94045:5"/>sincere plain-hearted man, that cannot dissemble, is caught; 'twas the devise against <hi>Daniel</hi> heretofore, They knew in the matters of his God 'twas easie to deal with him, because in those he would not upon any terms dissemble.</p>
            <p>This has Three ill Effects alwayes attending it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It disobliges the best sort of men in every party, whom the State should most cherish and engage; whatever is said to the contrary, those that are the truest Subjects to the Great King, will be also found the best to his Vicegerents here: 'Tis a strange Heterodox kind of policy, to make all the honest, sincere men in a Nation, of every party, but that one the State adheres to, the object of the States displeasure, and to make Laws that can have no other effect, but their Suffering.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All standers by, the generality of a Nation look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, must needs be dis-satisfied, to see a Plain honest man, upright and punctual in all his dealings amongst men, punished meerly for his Conscience to God; and because he will not comply to save himself, which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his Conscience can lead him to, and by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with which, he may at any time Purchase his quiet; in such a case common ingenuity begets pity for him, if not Proselytes to him, and great dislike of the course taken with him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though it be a secret, yet 'tis a very sure and certain way of bringing National Judgments upon a people; no doubt God takes great notice of the Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men meerly, because they are true to him, for so
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94045:6"/>every man is, that is true to his Conscience, though it be erroneous. Upon no other account was it, That <hi>Paul</hi> justified himself before the High-Priest, in say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>He had walked before God, in all good Conscience to that time.</hi> His meaning was, He had gone according to his Light, as a thing Pleasing to God, though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, as to the matter, his Conscience was errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and his iudgment mis-informed. And he tells us, afterwards, <hi>That he obtained Mercy from God,</hi> because what he did against the Church, was done Ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in pursuance of the best Light he then had.</p>
            <p>The punishing men meerly for following the pure dictates of Conscience, is no doubt the true cause of many National miseries; And a State should be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to avoid this, as they would preserve their own safety and Welfare. If we look into that which natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally occasioneth several Opinions in Religion, 'tis that which a Prince should for his own Interest highly encourage, and that is Knowledge; for no doubt, as Knowledge encreaseth, it expatiates it self into variety of Thoughts and Principles; and as it enlargeth all other Sciences, so Religion. Knowledge is the Glory of a Nation, and that by which all matters of Concern to it, as War, Trade, Policy, and every thing else is highly enlarged. 'Tis the high Honour of a Prince to Govern a Wise and a Knowing People, as well as a Great People; 'Tis an impotent piece of Policy, and equally destructive to all publick Interest, to say, <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects must be kept ignorant,</hi> as to say, <hi>They must be kept poor.</hi> They are Maxims only fitted for a Tyrant, and such who only govern for themselves, and calculate all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94045:6"/>Interests, as they concentre in their own, and by so doing, make themselves their own Idols. Nothing damps all Noble Undertakings amongst men of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, like Imposition in Religion, it makes them hang down their Heads, it makes them heartless in their Callings; If they are denied freedom in Religion, men of Conscience will care little for any thing else. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>A wounded Spirit no man can bear.</hi> He that carries a taint of trouble in his mind about these things, is impotent in every thing; 'tis Liberty in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that breeds the noble and generous minds. Let a man know his duty to God, and have freedom to perform it, and that man will have Wisdome and Courage above any man. Imposing Religion upon men has never other effect, than either to lull men asleep into implicite ignorance, and so make them as sottish and useless Members of a State, as they are of the Church; or else, where it meets with Knowledge and Integrity, sinks men under the greatest grief, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes them to the greatest dis-satisfaction. If we look amongst our selves, Who be they that desire favour in this particular? And who be they that will be grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and engaged by it, but every where men of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Principles? And are not they generally the sober and serious men, that bring good to a Nation? Are not they in all Gallings and Trades, generally most industrious, and thriving? Are not they most saving in their Expences, and every way, either in War or Peace, most useful and serviceable? 'Tis debauched, loose, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensive people that over-live their Estates, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect their Callings, that help to pull a state down; Such men will be sure to Conform to any thing, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94045:7"/>secures them in present Luxury; 'tis the sober, Serious, Religious sort of men, that every way make a Nation prosper; to discontent such, and to put them into one common Dungeon of imputed Faction, and actual Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution, will never be found any right measure of a true National Interest.</p>
            <p>Several things, with great Evidence, seem to plead for Moderation and Indulgence here in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Number and Quantity of those concerned, as well as the Quality is such, that it can be no way prudent to discontent them, upon that which will no way com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensate the inconvenience; there can be no good Policy to leave so many men, mixed every where, even in the highest places of the Nation, under dis-satisfaction, without the least effect, but the reproach of imprudence in doing it, and to put a disgraceful distinguishing Character upon, them, as men unfaithful to the State, only because they cannot comply with some Ceremonies (as the case is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally amongst us) and worship God just, in the publick way, a thing of no more intrinsick concern to the State, than to have all men of the same Opinion in a disputed point of Philosophy, and a thing of as equal likelihood to be attain'd. A Subject that gives the same testimony of his Fidelity to his Prince, that others do, and behaves himself in all Civil Concerns, as a faithful and profitable Member of the Commonwealth, and yet is looked upon as a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick enemy, and made the object of publick anger, because he cannot in every Circumstance comply with publick Religion, is without doubt very severely and impolitickly dealt with. As every Subject hath an Interest in his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94045:7"/>Prince, so hath the Prince in every Subject, and should be like the True Mother that would by no means divide the Child.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> be once fitly given, and the root of all mens hopes and pretensions, that desire publick mischief, is pulled up, and the King will be the greatest, and most Beloved Prince that ever yet sate upon the Throne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We shall never have a slourishing Trade without it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Because the Pressure in these things falls generally more upon the Trading sort of men, than any in the Nation; we may see it in the great City, and in all Corporations: It makes many give over Trading, and retire; It makes others remove into <hi>Holland,</hi> and other <hi>Forreign Parts;</hi> as it did heretofore from <hi>Norwich,</hi> to the irrecoverable prejudice of our Clothing Trade, upon the like occasion; And it certainly prevents all <hi>Protestant Strangers</hi> to come to Live and Trade amongst us. It puts great Advantages into the hands of the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander</hi> every way, who have not a better Friend in <hi>Europe,</hi> than <hi>Ʋniformity</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> As <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science</hi> here, is that they fear above any thing, so it would insensibly more weaken them, than all the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries we have obtained over them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Men will never Trade freely, where they do not Live and Converse freely; where a man is afraid to be watch'd to a Conventicle, and all the time he serves God,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94045:8"/>is fain to hide himself; No man will choose to live so, if he can avoid it; every man that cannot conform to the publick Religion, lying under the lash of the Law, will prudently shun both Business and Company, will never lay out his Estate, where 'tis in any mans power to do him a mischief. A man conscious to himself, that he cannot comply with the Law, will avoid medling with any thing, and choose privacy as his best security.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis the King of <hi>Englands</hi> true Interest to become Head of all the Protestant party in the World, and he will never do that, but by first making himself a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Father to all his Protestant Subjects at home. That 'tis his Interest to Head the Protestant party abroad, is plain; because being the greatest and most powerful of all Protestant Princes and States, he will necessarily draw them into a dependence upon him, and desire of Protection from him; by which not only the Protestant Interest in it self will be much secured, by being so united and conjoyned, but the King of <hi>England</hi> also will receive a great Accession of power, by the Influence he will have on so great a part of Christendom, which he may make use of, not only to secure the Protestant Religion against the common E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of it, but to advantage himself every way, by the great respect and Interest he will have in all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant States.</p>
            <p>To bring the Protestants into an union amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, will be of advantage to every Protestant State, but to none so much as <hi>England;</hi> First, Because <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94045:8"/>naturally becomes the Head of such a Union; And Secondly, Because the Designs and Practices of the Popish party, ever since the Reformation, have lain, and will lye more united against <hi>England,</hi> than any Protestant State, as supposing that the chief Support of all the rest; and therefore <hi>England</hi> can never be truly safe, nor secured in its proper Interest, but when 'tis invironed with all Protestant States adhering to it, and depending upon it. How sadly <hi>England</hi> has miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, when it has espoused any other collateral Interest but the Protestant, has been too obvious, ever since the first Reformation: <hi>England</hi> has been alwayes greatest at home, when it has been the greatest De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Protestant Faith abroad. Now if the King will thus rightly state his interest abroad, he must begin the Work at home; if he persecute and keep under any of his Protestant Subjects at home, those of their Opinion abroad, will never put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves under his protection: As he must make no distinction in Christendom, but <hi>Protestant</hi> and <hi>Papist,</hi> so he must make no other amongst his Subjects at home. He that imposeth any one Opinion amongst the <hi>Protestants,</hi> and will tolerate no other, makes the distinction to be still between <hi>Protestant</hi> and <hi>Protestant,</hi> and makes himself but Head of a Party amongst them, and will never so heed the <hi>Protestant</hi> Interest, as to oppose the <hi>Popish</hi> party with it, or unite the <hi>Protestants</hi> so under him, as to make himself their Head.</p>
            <p>Who ever would be Head of all the <hi>Protestant</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, must have no common Enemy but <hi>Popery,</hi> and concenter all there: Imposing Conformity to the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94045:9"/>of any one <hi>Protestant</hi> party, upon all the rest, is but to make himself so much the weaker by every dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senter, and is indeed totally destructive to the very being of such a thing.</p>
            <p>Lastly, Liberty of Conscience is the best way to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us to the Protestant Faith, and to prevent a relapse to Popery; the Protestant Religion will be fastest rooted, by exerting fully the Principles of it, and a throughout adhering to them; By our practice in deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one with another, to deny those Principles by which we justifie our Separation from <hi>Rome,</hi> is the ready way to make them return thither again. <hi>Teach men, that there is no man, nor men under any one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination, since the Apostles times, that are infallible in delivering Divine Truth. Teach men, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the only Rule, of Religion, and let them read it: Tell them, they are to follow no men, farther than they follow that Rule, and that every man is Judge according to the best Light he hath of that Rule, and how far other men comply with it, and differ from it: And that every man is bound to behave himself towards God, according to the Judgement he shall so make within himself;</hi> all which are Protestant Principles, and Eternal Truths. And then collect the sense which these principles issue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into; and how unreasonable will it then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to force men to comply with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he belief of others, contrary to their own; and when you have bid them use their Light and Reason, to punish them, because they will not oppose it, and go against it. How can we otherwise justifie forcing men, where such principles are avowed, but by a flat denial of them, and recur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94045:9"/>to those Popish Weapons of the absolute Power of the Church, and her uncontroulable Authority; and so by condemning others, that upon the exercise of their own Light and Reason now differ from us, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn our selves, who upon the same at first depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>Rome.</hi> When we oppose our selves upon the very same Arguments by which dissenters now amongst our selves make their defence against us; and when we dispute against them, we take up the same Argument the Papists use against us. There is scarce any consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Argument urged of late for Conformity, and Imposition, but if you trace it to the Seat, you shall find it in <hi>Bellarmine</hi> or <hi>Suarez.</hi> The truth is, He that cannot indure to have any differ from him in Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, about the Supernatural Truth of the Gospel, and will have no Toleration of several perswasions of that kind, and thinks it destructive to mankind, and the being of every State, to suffer any so to be; That man is a Protestant by mistake, and will find himself at home in his principles no where but at <hi>Rome.</hi> The farther we remove in our Reformation from the practice and Principles of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and live upon our own, the less like we are to return to it. If we make use of their Arguments and Principles at one time, we may come to use them at another, and at last espouse them all together; and what serves our turn at some times to oppose others, may at last prevail upon our selves. And so 'tis in our practices, reserving any of their Ceremonies, may at last bring us to some of their Doctrines. He that keeps a Holiday, is within a step of praying to that Saint, for whose sake he keeps it, specially if he have the wit to consider why he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94045:10"/>keeps it. He that kneels, and puts weight upon it, is in a fair way to adoration: and he that is for joyning the Cross with Baptism, may come to do it after Grace, and cross himself in time. 'Twas Bishop <hi>Bonners</hi> observation, when he saw the Reformation, and how many of the Popish Ceremonies were retained, being asked what he thought of it, <hi>If they like</hi> (saith he) <hi>the tast of our Broth so well, they will eat of our Beef shortly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Liberty of Conscience is the great means to diffuse Gospel-Knowledge in Divine things, and that's the best and surest way to bar out Popery, and lock the door upon it for ever. Ignorance is the great and only preparative for implicite Subjection. Christendom cannot (I dare say) afford an instance that ever any State or People, where Divine-Knowledge, by Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conscience, and a Liberty for the Gospel was spread, were in the least danger of turning Apostates to Popery, but have grown daily more and more into a detestation of it, and generally almost every man amongst them, carrying a Weapon in his understanding to defend the Protestant Cause.</p>
            <p>Were Liberty of Conscience granted in <hi>Italy,</hi> and other Popish States, we should soon see the Mitre totter upon the Popes head, and probably see as fair Churches there, as in any other part of <hi>Europe.</hi> 'Twas observed in the Wars of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> That when ever any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick began to look into the Bible, he was not long liv'd in the Roman Profession.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Liberty of Conscience will breed men up with an irreconcileable dislike to all imposition in Religion and Conscience, and so unite them in a general ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94045:10"/>of Popery, as the Grandmother and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it. All Christendom over, all principles and parties born from a Liberty given in Religion, have an Antipathy in them to that Romish Yoke, and do naturally unite against the Popish Religion, as the grand and common Enemy of them all.</p>
            <p>Let Liberty of Conscience once be given in a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant State, and though there be never so many diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences amongst themselves, yet men of all perswasions will concenter in that. He that has the freedom of his Religion, will be concerned to defend it, and look upon Popery as the great Gyant he is in danger of. Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and Fact, the best of all demonstrations, do evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence this: take a view of those places, where Liberty of Conscience hath been most given, and you will find there the greatest aversion to Popery, that is in any parts of Christendom.</p>
            <p>'Tis in other places, where other Methods of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition and Persecution are used, that compliance with Popery hath been attempted, and projects set on foot to compound the Protestant and the Papists into an agreement.</p>
            <p>'Tis Imposition in Religion sweeps the house, and keeps the Nest warm for Popery: Liberty of Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence mortally stabs lit; where that is once given, it may be said to the Pope, as it was to <hi>Belshazzar; God hath numbred thy Kingdom, and finished it, and the place where he once tyrannized, shall know him there no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, If the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> understand their own Interest, as we have good reason to believe they do, this Case is determined to our hands; for upon every occasion since the reformation, both in <hi>Germany,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94045:11"/>France, Swisserland,</hi> and all places where Liberty of Conscience hath been endeavoured, the Popes have <hi>toto animo</hi> every way opposed it, and declared it a thing perfectly destructive to the Church, and such, as where ever it was suffered, would destroy the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Faith; and in that Maxime, I believe their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility is not much to be denied. Some are so much otherwise minded, that they believe Liberty of Conscience will be the ready means to induce Popery again amongst us, the reasons of it seem invisible, unless it be to be done by some new Rule of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries; it must either come to pass, by giving liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in general to Protestants of differing perswasions, or else by giving liberty to the Papists themselves, as included in a general Liberty. For the first (I hope) it appears evidently to have another tendency.</p>
            <p>And for the second, The giving Liberty to the Papists themselves amongst us, no man well informed, can imagine that they should be included in any such Liberty.</p>
            <p>Because in their practice amongst us, they refuse to give that publick assurance, every Subject ought to give of his fidelity that expects the favour due to a Subject.</p>
            <p>And also Because their Principles are such, That if they derstand their own Religion, they can never be good Subjects to any Protestant State: He that knows not this, knows not the Roman Religion, and to prove it so by Fact.</p>
            <p>Amongst very many other Instances, let what was done here in the time of <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> to her; and at the same time in <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, for ever lie upon Record against them. Nor can a Papist ever become a true and hearty Subject to a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Prince, but by that act he ceaseth to be so. And
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94045:11"/>as common justice does deny them all pretensions to Liberty, so common equity opposeth them; for as both they and their Religion abhor giving Liberty to any but themselves, so is their practice accordingly, for they never give liberty to a Soul living, that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from them, where they are able and dare deny it.</p>
            <p>To say, That Liberty of Conscience can have no other effect, but to tolerate damnable Heresies, and all kind of Sectaries, which is the usual way of discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing it; and so to enlarge into all kind of satyrical Rhetorick upon that Topick, is to put a Bears skin upon it, and then to hair it. 'Twill be to impose a thing of a very hard belief upon me, to say, That Truth never gains by Liberty, and that the Imposer is alwayes in the right, and the sufferer in the wrong; especially considering, he that thinks me an Heretick, another thinks him so, and a fourth thinks us all so; and all the while we are all of us weak, imperfect, fallible men, sitting in judgment, and sentencing one another; And there can be no other end of it, but that he that is strongest, makes himself in the right, and destroys the rest. When ever Truth comes to suffer by Imposition, as many times it does, and comes afterwards to be so acknowledged, the evil of such Imposition carries its own evidence. But suppose such Truth never gets any good, and Liberty should be only to men under Errors and Mistakes, 'twere not fit then to deny it, that is, 'twere not fit then to impose upon them; for Liberty is nothing but a Negative upon Force and Imposition; If we consult the good of such men themselves, so lapsed into Error, and desire their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version, Force and Imposition is no way to it; If we consult
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94045:12"/>our own Security, there is no danger at all can come by it; for as long as such errors lye in the understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and are only conversant about supernatural things, they have no reference at all to the being or well-being of Mankind, as such: What hurt does an Error in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion do me in my Neighbour, that is otherwise an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest and good man? He is rather in that an Object of my pity, and instruction, than of my anger.</p>
            <p>If we desire to have all men of our Opinion, because we think we are in the right, 'tis a very commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing; and if we do it with such a publick Charity, we shall use only such Christian means, as naturally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to bring it about. But if through the pride of mens hearts, and the intention of their own exaltation thereby, they will have every body of their Opinion; and because they cannot convince and perswade them, will therefore force them, and trample upon them, that's an odious superintendency.</p>
            <p>To say, That upon a prudential Account, Liberty should never be allow'd in State, because 'tis that which will unite Parties, and bring them to a Consistency amongst themselves, and so render them much more dangerous, is to say a thing upon a great mistake. For common experience shews us. That nothing unites par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties more amongst themselves, than a not Persecution; nor does any thing bring them so much together as that; 'tis like a great Storm, that drives. Cattel, that are scattered about, altogether, and brings them to meet in one common shelter to save themselves.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:94045:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ridley</hi> and <hi>Hooper</hi> agreed in the Goal, that would hardly have disputed themselves Friends.</p>
            <p>There is no bond of union amongst disagreeing Persons, like Persecution; the common concern of their Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then begets Correspondency, Acquaintance, and such Intercourse and mutual Assistance, as endears them above any thing one to another. And for the danger there may be of any party, there is nothing sure so like to remove that, as Indulging them with a Liberty: the best way to be secured against the discontent of any party, is to remove the cause of such discontent; and the best way to be out of fear of them, unless you can totally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy them, is to oblige them, and so at once to engage and win them over, and thereby disband our own fears.</p>
            <p>A Modern Author tells us with particular remark, That <hi>Maecenus</hi> heretofore gave advice to <hi>Augustus, That upon no terms he should endure such, who would bring in any strange Worship into the State.</hi> I believe it, and 'twas such kind of Advice (no doubt) that caused the ten first Persecutions.</p>
            <p>Methinks the Author should have remembred, that that Advice would have kept Christianity out of the World: For, if we follow the track of such Policy, we shall find, that what we now say against Tolerating Dissenters amongst our selves, The Papists first said, and do still say against us all; and if we go one step higher, the Heathens said the very same against the Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it self, and thought it a Factious, Fanatick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of sick-brain'd men, and a thing not to be endured,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94045:13"/>that men should not content themselves with the same Gods that the rest of the World worshiped and acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>esced in. 'Tis a sad thing and much to be lamented, That the Protestants should take up the dregs of those Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks, and make use of them one against another, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every small difference amongst themselves.</p>
            <p>The same Auther, in anothor part of his Book, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds this question,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If divers ways of Worship</hi> (saith he) <hi>be allowed in a Nation, What shall a Prince do? If he keep any men of any Profession or Party out of employment for their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion sake, he disobliges that party; If he bring all men indifferently alike into employment, if he be of any party himself, he will disoblige his own party, who will expect preheminence in that kind, and so in conclusion, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to please all, he will lose all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a knot very easily untyed. I will suppose a Prince strict in the Profession and Practice of what he thinks is the Truth; and the more strict personally he is, the greater will the favour of Indulgence appear to those that differ from him: but there is no necessity, that he should make a party of those, who are of his Opinion, distinct from the rest of his Subjects; 'tis below his Greatness, and besides his Interest so to do; they will soon become like the Sons of <hi>Zeruiah,</hi> Those that are of his Opinion, he may think them, in his private judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, better Christians than others; but there is no Policy so to distinguish them, as if they were thereby better Subjects than others.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:94045:13"/>
            <p> All men in a State, are to give one common Assurance of their Fidelity, and such who are allowed a Liberty in their Religion, when differing from the publick Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession; the Political end of it is, to make them good Subjects; and the end of that must needs be, to make them serviceable to their Prince; and there is no reason to doubt, but that they will be so, and eminently so, because they lye under an Obligation to his Favour, those of his own Opinion are not capable of. A Prince should seat himself in his Throne, with an equal Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Aspect to all his Subjects, and employ them, as their fitness for his Service qualifies them: There is no reason to narrow and limit a Prince to any Party, or to let any Party grow into such a predominant Opinion, as if the Prince were confined to them.</p>
            <p>No mans bare Opinion in such things should qualifie him for an employment, nor no mans Opinion ought to put a Negative upon him in that kind; that is for a Prince, after he has obliged all his Subjects to him, to lose the use of a great part of them. Let a Prince but choose men to serve him, whose Ability and Fitness car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the evidence of his choice, and other Exceptions will soon vanish. 'Tis below the greatness of a Prince, to have any Subject pretend to employment, upon any score, but his judgment of his fitness for it.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>France</hi> hath heretofore often with good success employed his Protestant Subjects; Nay, has often trusted the Command of his whole Army in the hand of a Protestant, and yet feared not the disobliging of the Popish party, or being thought a man of no Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94045:14"/>for so doing. 'Tis a most absurd and impolitick thing, because men differ in some divine supernatural things, to put them under such Characters, as to make them unuseful one to another, in all other humane things.</p>
            <p>Let a Prince once give Liberty of Conscience, and he obliges all Parties to him, and makes them wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon him; the tenure of their Liberty will be a tenure <hi>in Capite,</hi> and <hi>Quam diu se bene gesserint;</hi> and for employing men, and dispensing favours to them, let all Parties with a due subjection lye under the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative and Soveraignty of his pleasure.</p>
            <p>Two things are with much earnestness usually Object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed against the grant of Liberty;</p>
            <p>First, <hi>That it is unbecomming the Zeal and Concern a Magistrate should have for the Truth of Religion, to give Liberty to any thing, but what he thinks to be so, and that such a lukewarmness, as Liberty to several Opinions supposeth, does no way become him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Second, <hi>That giving Liberty to men of several Opinions, is the way to propagate and encrease them, and is of great danger to a State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the First, It is very fit that the Magistrate should espouse, what he thinks to be the Truth, and keep him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to a strict practice of it, and use all lawful means to possess others with it; let him use all the means Christ and the Apostles used to Convince and Convert
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94045:14"/>men; but let him not lay violent hands upon mens persons, because he cannot satisfie their understandings; that is Zeal without Knowledge, and Religion without a Rule, either in Reason or Divinity; that is to run into so wide an extream from <hi>Laodicaean</hi> lukewarmness, as to become like <hi>Paul</hi> before his Coversion, who saith of himself, <hi>that he was mad, persecuting the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To say a Magistrate is lukewarm in Religion, because he will not force men to his Opinion, is to say, He is lukewarm, because he will not do a thing, that Christ hath no where required of him; and do a thing, that is to no purpose to do, for that very end for which it is done.</p>
            <p>Tolerating men has no more in it, than not forcing men, 'tis only a Negative favour, there is nothing Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative in it; a Magistrate will never be charged with Lukewarmness in Religion, that makes use of all Gospel-means to promote Truth, and that he may do, and yet never violate the due Liberty of any mans Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. If we consult the antient practice of the first Christian Magistrates; we shall find it plain, That Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conscience was given by the Christian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. <hi>Constantine</hi> did it fully. <hi>Eusebius</hi> in his life tells us, that he made a Decree in these words, <hi>Ut parem cum fidelibus, ii qui errant, pacis &amp; quietis fruitionem gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentis accipiant.</hi> 'Tis true, he banished <hi>Arius;</hi> but let any man consult the Ecclesiastical History, and he shall find <hi>Arius</hi> so factious and base a person, that there need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no part of his Opinion to be the cause of his exile, <hi>Gratian</hi> the Emperour made likewise a Decree for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94045:15"/>in Religion. The <hi>Jews</hi> had granted by all the Emperours, the same Rights with other Christians. <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinian</hi> and <hi>Valentinian,</hi> most noble Princes, suffered Christians of several perswasions, to enjoy their Liberty: Of this, <hi>Grotius</hi> in his Book <hi>De Imp. Sum. Potes. Circ. Sac. Cap.</hi> 8. takes particular notice, adding these words, and saith he, which is more to be noted, <hi>The Emperour did not only permit impunity to disagreeing Sects, but often made Laws to order their Assemblies.</hi> Liberty therefore in Religion is not either so new, or so strange a thing, or so great a Monster, as men would make it. State-Religions are not always infallibly true, Truth some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times keeps men from embracing them, it does so in many parts of Christendom; and in that case a Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Restraint upon the Magistrates compulsion, is the only shelter of Truth. The Wisdom of Christ, who hath forbid the use of the Temporal power under the Gospel, about Religion, hath left things best. For if a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate be in the right, he may promote Truth, as far as in the nature of the thing, and by Christs appointment, it can be promoted; if he be not in the right, where the Temporal power does not interpose, men are secured in the profession of Truth, and not hazard in refusing a publick error.</p>
            <p>He that would have the Magistrate force all men to his Religion, will himself be burnt by his own Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, when he comes into a Country, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here the State-Religion differs from him: To say, He is in the right, and the State that does it in the wrong, is a miserable begging the Question. If one Magistrate be to do it, all are to do it, and there can be no other rule of Truth and Error in that case, but what they think so. If a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94045:15"/>Magistrate be once admitted to punish with death, what is really and truly in it self an Heresie, he may, and must by the same rule so punish every thing he thinks so; Where shall the definition of Heresie terminate, and who shall set the Magistrate bounds in such a case? Misinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Passion, or some sinister Interest, can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lead men into such Principles, which tend to nothing, but to make Religion disturb the Peace and Quiet of all mankind; and as one saith well, <hi>to bring Christians to a butchery one of another, and to make a meer Shambles of Christendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Second Objection, <hi>That giving liberty to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Parties, encreaseth them, and makes them danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to a State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, 'Tis very fit, that wheresoever you will suppose Errors to be sprung up, all the means Christ hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that end, should be used to suppress them, and reclaim men from them; let their mouths be stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with sound Doctrine, and spiritual Censures; the only Question is about the use of the Temporal power in such things: And experience tell us, That since the World began, to this day, Principles and Opinions in the mind were never extinguished by the punishing the body; That old saying verifies it,</p>
            <q>Sanguis Martyrum, semen Ecclesiae.</q>
            <p>Nay, there is nothing under the Sun to promote a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Opinion in Religion, like making men suffer for it; the constancy and courage of men in suffering for an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94045:16"/>will sooner perswade men to it, than all the Discourses and Sermons in the World.</p>
            <p>If the Magistrate take a violent course to root out all different Opinions in Religion, such as the Emperors heretofore, when Heathen, took with the Christians, and the Popish States, where they are able, do at this day with the Protestants; besides the cruelty of it, with which he will besmear himself, he will miss of his end, and find a succession of those Principles in others, rising out of the Ashes of those he destroys, as it used to be said heretofore by the Martyrs,
<q>Quoties morimur, toties nascimur.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If he take a mild and more gentle way of persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he only exasperates them, and then leaves them armed with all possible discontent.</p>
            <p>Consider the giving of Liberty under these two heads.</p>
            <p>First, the giving of it to several Opinions and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, where they are already actually existing.</p>
            <p>And secondly, The givng Liberty so, as will occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and produce such Parties and Opinions.</p>
            <p>For the first, Where there are several Parties in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion already in being, and diffused all over a Nation, as the Case is with us, it is the best way to indulge them, for they are by their number outgrown the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical part of persecution.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:94045:16"/>
            <p> For the second, Consideration of Liberty, the giving it so as will naturally produce several Principles and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in men, he that would prevent that, must give no Liberty to the Protestant Religion, must not let the Bible be read by the Vulgar: There is no way to keep out seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Opinions in Religion, but an implicit ignorant sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to an imposed Infallibility, and to do as the <hi>Turks</hi> do, who will not have any Learning or Discourse amongst them of Religion, for that very Reason, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they will have no Religion but <hi>Mahomet,</hi> nor no Learning but the <hi>Alcoran;</hi> such policy to murder mens Souls is hatched in Hell.</p>
            <p>The very ART of PRINTING was at the first thought dangerous, because it was looked on as a thing like to introduce several Opinions in Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cardinal</hi> Woolsey, <hi>in a Letter of his to the Pope, hath this passage about it.</hi> That his Holiness could not be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant what divers effects the new Invention of PRINTING had produced; for as it had brought in and restored Books and Learning, so together it hath been the occasion of those Sects and Schisms which daily appeared in the World, but chiefly in <hi>Germany,</hi> where men begin now to call in question the present Faith and Tenents of the Church, and to examine how far Religion is departed from its Primitive Institution. And that which particularly was most to be lamented, they had exhorted Lay and Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Men to read the Scriptures, and to pray in their Vulgar Tongue. That, if this were suffered, besides all other dangers, the common People at last might come to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there was not so much use of the Clergy; for if men were perswaded once they could make their own
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94045:17"/>way to God, and that Prayers in their Native and Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Language might pierce Heaven, as well as Latin; How much would the Authority of the Mass fall? How preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial might this prove unto all our Ecclesiastical Orders? Lord <hi>Herberts</hi> Hist. of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth.</p>
            <p>Liberty of Conscience lies as naturally necessary to a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant State, as Imposition to a Popish State; he must be a good Artist that can find a right middle way between these two. 'Tis the Glory of Protestant States to have much of the knowledge of God amongst them, and that variety of mens Opinions, about some less weighty, and more obscure matters of Religion, as it much tends to a discovery of the Truth of them, so it no way breaks the Bond of Protestant Union, where men generally agree in the same Rule of Religion, and in all the chief and necessary Fundamentals of Salvation. Liberty of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in such States, as it is their true and genuine Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, and without which they will but deny themselves those advantages they might otherwise arrive at; so with the forementioned <hi>Boundaries,</hi> can never prove hurtful or dangerous, there being always a just distinction to be made between those who desire only to serve God, and such who pretend that, to become injurious to men. And thus we have seen, that not only Religion but Reason, not only Duty but Interest, do invocate Princes and States in this Particular: To whom it may fitly be said in the words of the Psalmist, <hi>Be wise now therefore, O ye Kings, and be instructed, O ye Judges of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall now add, by way of Post-script, a Citation out of an ingenious Book, Entituled, <hi>An Humble Apology for Nonconformists,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:94045:17"/>
            <head>Post-script.</head>
            <p>HAD you rather that <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Romish Seducers</hi> should gather up Multitudes; and that Taverns, Alehouses, and worse places, should on the Lords day be filled with the number of those that absent themselves from the publick Assemblies, rather than that they should be tolerated to hear a Sermon of Faith and Repentance, and other Duties towards God, and of Loyalty to the King, of Love and Charity one towards another, in a private house? For my own part, I confess in this Case, I would much rather go learn what that means, <hi>The Harvest truly is great, and the Labourers are few: pray ye therefore the Lord of the Harvest, that he would send forth Labourers into his Harvest.</hi> Again, it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, that Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hildersham,</hi> and others, were silenced formerly but in some Diocesses, and for some time; afterwards they got divers times liberty to preach. Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> had a License to preach, under the broad Seal of <hi>England,</hi> procured by Bishop <hi>Williams,</hi> then Lord Keeper, notwithstanding his Inconformity. Mr. <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> notwithstanding he had writ so much, and so sharply against Conformity, was suffered to preach, and enjoyed a place of Master of an Hospital at <hi>Warwick,</hi> to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94045:18"/>his dying day. Yea, Mr, <hi>Brown,</hi> the Father of the <hi>Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists,</hi> if we believe the Historian, was suffered to keep a Living, and that no mean one, (<hi>Achurch</hi> in <hi>Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonshire</hi>) to his Death. The Bishops in those dayes, if they turned Men out of their Pulpits, let them have a Livelihood; either some way from their Livings, or else permitted them, or connived at least at their teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of School. My Schoolmaster at a Grammer School, was one that had left a Living, rather than he would Conform. And 'tis storied of old Mr. <hi>John Fox,</hi> by Doctor <hi>Heylyn,</hi> that though he refused to subscribe to any thing but the Greek Testament, yet he enjoyed his Prebonds place in <hi>Salisbury</hi> till his dying day. 'Tis worthy our notice, that these mens Yoak was more easie than ours: And that notwithstanding they are thought to be of different Principles from the present <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> yet certain it is, that they held it lawful to preach and pray, and keep days of Humiliation in private Houses. And I was told by one Mr. <hi>W.</hi> That <hi>he never had any other Ordination but Prayers and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of hands; by old Mr.</hi> Dod, <hi>and some other Ministers his Friends, in a private House.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the consideration of the Premises, my hearts desire is, That the present Age may labour to <hi>imitate,</hi> and <hi>surpass</hi> the Age past; the Right Reverend the Bishops their Predecessors, in their Forbearance and Moderation; and the <hi>Nonconformists</hi> theirs, in their Meekness and Peaceableness; That the Bishops would endeavour to be Reconcilers, and Repairers of our Breaches, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storers of our Pulpits to preach in; and that the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> would desire nothing but what may become Sons of Peace. and such as earnestly long after Unity,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94045:18"/>and had much rather, as becomes Labourers, be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to work in the Vineyard, than to stand any longer idle in the Market-place: Or as becomes Fishers of Men, to be casting their Nets on the right side of the Ship, than to sit any longer mending their Nets on the Shore. That so the Ages to come, when they shall read the History of this Generation, when we all (<hi>Conformists</hi> and <hi>Nonconformists</hi>) are laid down to rest quietly together in our Graves, may have no occasion to rise up and say, <hi>That whereas the late War had made its thousands of Separatists, Rigid Conformity had made its ten thousands:</hi> And all too, during the peaceable Reign of our most Gracious Soveraign, (a Son of Peace) <hi>CHARLES the Clement;</hi> as he hath manifested himself, by his Royal Letters and Declaration from <hi>Breda,</hi> his Royal Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations since, and his present Princely Clemency; And this too, notwithstanding great Animosities, Exaspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and Irritations of some, on the one hand, out of an inordinate Zeal; and many Weaknesses, Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and Provocations of some on the other, for lack of Knowledge.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>